<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://danny.page/views/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://danny.page/views/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-10T16:00:29+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Danny Page - Page Views</title><subtitle>Danny Page's articles, code snippets, and other things to store and share.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">CapFriendly Systems Design</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/CapFriendly-Systems-Design" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CapFriendly Systems Design" /><published>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/CapFriendly-Systems-Design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/CapFriendly-Systems-Design">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://capfriendly.com&quot;&gt;CapFriendly&lt;/a&gt; was a website for hockey fans, the media, and even teams (they were so indispensible, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espn.com/nhl/story/_/id/40337498/capitals-announce-deal-buy-nhl-salary-data-site-capfriendly&quot;&gt;they were acquired by the Washington Capitals&lt;/a&gt;). They covered many different facets in hockey player management: salary caps, draft inventory, transactions, and more. All while handling millions of visitors every month and keeping up with the Free Agency rush every July. It’s a monumental feat and one that should be celebrated for others to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve interviewed for many Software Engineer roles that put a heavy emphasis on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systems_design#Web_System_design&quot;&gt;Systems Design&lt;/a&gt;. As a full-stack engineer, part of the job is knowing how the whole system fits together. Perhaps you can write really efficient code and solve LeetCode problems, but can you explain the purpose of the system? How should different applications interact and solve those requirements? What should the database schema look like? Who will use it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dig into some of the major areas of CapFriendly’s system design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;product-requirements&quot;&gt;Product Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are people going to come to the website for? How can we serve a variety of customers? How will it make money?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CapFriendly, like CapGeek before it, was launched to help fans to better understand how teams in the NHL were managing their rosters and their salary caps. Before those sites were around, many contract details were hidden from the public. Teams would often not willingly disclose salary or term length, or if there were any No Move/Trade Clauses. Media members could get this info, but it wasn’t in one place. So the ultimate &lt;em&gt;raison d’être&lt;/em&gt; of these cap sites: &lt;strong&gt;Get contract data to the public.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the site’s major features flow neatly from this requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Cap Space and Assets&lt;/strong&gt;  - Are teams in compliance? What draft picks do they hold? Retained salaries?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player Salary Lookup&lt;/strong&gt; - Who can fit into your favorite teams?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculators&lt;/strong&gt; - What if scenarios: What’s the cap hit on buying out a contract? Offer Sheets?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transactions&lt;/strong&gt; - Trades, Drafts, Waives, Signings, Injuries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulators&lt;/strong&gt; - Let fans get into the mindset of a GM by giving them easy tools to make transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these features can be accomplished with two primary ingredients: contract and transaction data, and knowing the rules that govern those contracts and transactions. The latter also makes the site extremely useful in acquisition; the people running the site have been trusted by the teams and clearly understand the nuances of managing the team’s resources. While fans were the primary goal, it’s revealing that media and teams leaned on the website as well. Having all this data in a central &amp;amp; public repository was seen as unnecessary thing by the league; clearly many stakeholders at clubs and journalists disagreed with the NHL on this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website would eventually lean on ads and a premium service to make money; quite necessary when the traffic of the site was easily in the millions of users per month. Becoming a massive hit is an exciting prospect but also brings plenty of issues. Scaling the tech, paying for more servers, and finding ways to get paid can stress a small team of developers. I believe they may have done some deals with teams; this would surely solve some monetary problems and subsidize the public traffic, but it also represents a diverging sets of interests. The public may want features that go in line with the original purpose of public contract and cap data. The teams would instead need features that would help the team win. We’ll never get to see how the site would continue to evolve to fit the public’s needs; instead the system’s purpose will be changed to “how can the Capitals win?” which will require a much different system. (More on that later)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;major-components&quot;&gt;Major Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What applications will be needed? Which database is right for the handling of data? What APIs will we interface with to get external data? What web framework will be used?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/IMG_0111.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;general systems design map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without knowing the internals of the website, I can surmise some of the major portions of their system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Admin Panel
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Media reports, scouting reports, trade entries, transactions: all of this would need to be entered into the system. There are multiple libraries that handle this data entry + data validation. Contract entry would need to have multiple things checked off before it could be submitted into the system. Or in the case of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salaryswish.com/trades/players/reggie-jackson&quot;&gt;six-way-trade&lt;/a&gt; entering what teams are involved, making sure they have the assets that the trade is using, and what conditionals are in place.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public facing app
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Everything that we see. Team dashboards, player history, the forums, the Armchair GM tool, etc. Given the JavaScript-lite nature of the website, I’ll guess that it’s a Django or Ruby on Rails app that does a lot of server rendering. This can be a big benefit for mostly-read-only website; caching and load balancing is much easier with these setups.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Database
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The secret sauce of the website. The hard work. Some may say it’s easy to build such a website, but the difficulty is understanding and gathering all the data necessary to populate it. Calculating daily cap hits requires perfect data about player contracts, transactions, and business rules.
        &lt;h2 id=&quot;data-model&quot;&gt;Data Model&lt;/h2&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website would need to keep track of the following. Some of these may need snapshots at any given day, especially the cap hit tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple storage: Teams, Players, Trades, Waivers, Drafts, Scouting Reports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Materialized) Views: UFAs, League Cap Dashboard, Team Cap Dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forum posts, Threads, Users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Armchair GM teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to call out the last part, because it’s what made the site special for many hardcore users. While I’d guess 99% of users just looked up their favorite team or pending UFAs, 1% of users created many, many Armchair GM teams. Around 1.5 URLs in my big crawl were related to this feature. Storing these user-created teams requires it’s own set of database tables so that it can store the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the current contracts for players?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the current salary cap?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the depth chart look like? What should special teams look like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What trades could be made to create this new team?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What other transactions are necessary (waiving, LTIR, buyouts, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has to be stored away from the main data. It could have been all done on the front-end and not saved in a database like my &lt;a href=&quot;https://danny.page/expected_goals&quot;&gt;Expected Goals calculator&lt;/a&gt;, so a big kudos to the CapFriendly team giving people the fantasy of modifying their favorite team and building conversations around it in the Forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-considerations&quot;&gt;Other considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to consider are questions around scaling the website, caching pages, user registration, forum moderation. There’s also the API that partners could use; I also did not dive deep into their premium offerings. The transformations and calculations to project out many years. All of this takes a lot of different skills and expertise, both in the general software development and business specific needs. I hope to do more architecture reviews in the future and cover these aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of July 10th, CapFriendly is no longer public. They’ve closed the site and now are full time members of the Washington Capitals. Chris Patrick has been promoted to General Manager and needs to improve and change the product for the Caps Front Office. What might they do with the application? Here are a few things I’d suggest they take to make the best use of the software already created:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a front office user, I want to securely access the site, so that it’s protected and I have access to add notes on players and teams. // SSO logins will protect this, train folks on how to use the backend for adding data as necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a scout, I want to be able to add scouting reports directly on each page, so that it can be one place. // Create a place on every page that lets the most recent notes be seen. Pivot the page from just being about to contract, to a one-stop shop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a data analyst, I want to have up-to-date stats, so that we make better decisions //  Use the integration framework to bring in data about each player, whether that’s continuing to pay for data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eliteprospects.com/&quot;&gt;Elite Prospects&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolving-hockey.com/&quot;&gt;Evolving Hockey&lt;/a&gt; or building it in-house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the goal is to use CapFriendly like a salesperson might use Salesforce: It’s a one-stop shop for many people to collaborate and make decisions, all while having a single source of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-archive&quot;&gt;The Archive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While CapFriendly is now offline for most of us, what’s next? First, &lt;a href=&quot;https://puckpedia.com/&quot;&gt;PuckPedia&lt;/a&gt; has done a fantastic job of picking up the baton. But if you’re nostalgic for CapFriendy, need to double check some data, or just want to relive some of your Armchair GM teams, I’ve created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/capfriendly-warc-archive&quot;&gt;WARC archive on the Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; that crawled the site shortly before the shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capfriendly-full-crawl-2024-07-05.warc.gz - This is 44GB and contains all the forums. If it wasn’t captured here, it’s not going to be in any other archive. Crawled from July 5th to July 8th. (Over 2.5M web requests!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capfriendly-short-crawl-no-forums-2024-07-09.warc.gz - This is 775MB and Is very lightweight. It has the teams and most of the players, but may be missing some data. I captured this on July 9th, right before the shutdown.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;capfriendly-short-crawl-no-forums-2024-07-03.warc.gz - Crawled July 3rd after the free agent rush, and is 3GB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to view these files like the Wayback Machine, there are a few options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://replayweb.page/&quot;&gt;Replay Webpage&lt;/a&gt; - Useful for the lightweight crawls: It is totally in-browser. Download the file, load it into the page, and then navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://www.capfriendly.com&lt;/code&gt; when prompted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/webrecorder/pywb&quot;&gt;pywb&lt;/a&gt; - Python library for capturing and serving archives. This is the ideal setup for researchers (or &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; teams) - Download the 3 archives and run this as a server. To do that:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir cf-archive &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd cf-archive
$ python3 -m venv archive-venv
$ source archive-venv/bin/activate
$ pip install pywb
// follow the instructions at https://pywb.readthedocs.io/en/latest/manual/usage.html#using-existing-web-archive-collections to setup the archives that you downloaded
$ wayback
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then go to the server and search for the main URL - and then you’ll have it running locally!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/IMG_0110.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot of PYWB running with the archive showing the capfriendly homepage as captured on July 9th&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-closing&quot;&gt;In Closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this was useful, and I want to provide my congratulations to the Davis’s and (selfishly) I hope this means great things for the Washington Capitals. But I also share the bittersweet feelings that a public resource was lost. It must have been a difficult decision to shut down something that had been beloved by so many people. Hopefully this article can help people appreciate the hard work they did and revisit it if they so choose by checking out the archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this article, please reach out to me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:questions@danny.page&quot;&gt;my email&lt;/a&gt; or my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/danielwpage&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">CapFriendly was a website for hockey fans, the media, and even teams (they were so indispensible, they were acquired by the Washington Capitals). They covered many different facets in hockey player management: salary caps, draft inventory, transactions, and more. All while handling millions of visitors every month and keeping up with the Free Agency rush every July. It’s a monumental feat and one that should be celebrated for others to learn from.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tracking Fireworks Impact on Fourth of July AQI</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/tracking-fireworks-on-july-4th" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tracking Fireworks Impact on Fourth of July AQI" /><published>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/tracking-fireworks-on-july-4th</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/tracking-fireworks-on-july-4th">&lt;p&gt;I’m increasingly of the opinion that fireworks should not be used at all, or at best sparingly in the best conditions for safe dispersal of the pollutants. There are fire risks, limb risks, and breathing risks that come with exploding toxic chemicals in the air. However, America disagrees with me, especially at 8:45 PM local time on July 4th each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.purpleair.com/&quot;&gt;PurpleAir&lt;/a&gt; after spending a few years in California and having to adjust my life when wildfire smoke was around. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airnow.gov/national-maps/&quot;&gt;US Government’s Air Quality map&lt;/a&gt; usually lags what you can see in the air. Often times I’d open it when it was dreadfully obvious that it was a 150-200 PM2.5 AQI day, and it was still reporting under 100. Only after multiple days of requiring a N95 and clothes smelling like a campfire would it be updated. Fortunately, many people have adjusted by buying PurpleAir monitors and you can see live-to-the-minute information about the air quality around you on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://map.purpleair.com/&quot;&gt;PurpleAir map.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/fireworks/dc-purpleair.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this massive and real-time map, you can see the effects of fireworks can be acutely and suddenly be seen on the national scale. I remembered to check this site after hearing fireworks in the DC area. You can quite clearly see various monitors noting massive rises in the AQI metric in the evening of July 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/fireworks/dc-purpleair-graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having missed my chance for watching this unfold in DC, I turned my attention to the San Francisco Bay Area. I setup &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/simonw/shot-scraper?tab=readme-ov-file&quot;&gt;Shot-Scraper&lt;/a&gt;, a Python command line library, that opens a headless browser, waits a few second, and then takes a screenshot. I installed the library in its own virtual environment, created a folder for the images, and fired off a few test screenshots to make sure it looked good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir purpleair &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd purpleair
$ python3 -m venv venv 
$ source venv/bin/activate
$ pip install shot-scraper
$ mkdir images
$ shot-scraper https://map.purpleair.com/1/mAQI/a10/p604800/cC0#8.45/37.764/-121.62 --wait 5000 -o ~/Projects/images/bay-area-$(date +%Y%m%d_%H%M%S).png`

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/fireworks/bay-area-20240704_220000.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I eventually landed on. The first shot was at 10 PM EDT, or 7 PM local. You could see there were a few hot spots already; unclear if those were fireworks related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had it creating screenshots via the command line, I needed a script to activate the Python environment and trigger the command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/Projects/purpleair
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;source &lt;/span&gt;venv/bin/activate

shot-scraper https://map.purpleair.com/1/mAQI/a10/p604800/cC0#8.45/37.764/-121.62 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--wait&lt;/span&gt; 5000 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-o&lt;/span&gt; /Users/dpage/Projects/purpleair/images/bay-area-&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt; +%Y%m%d_%H%M%S&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.png

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ crontab -e&lt;/code&gt; command, I added an entry to fire off that script every minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;*/1 * * * * ~/Projects/purpleair/scraper.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I let it run overnight. After 12 hours of running, I had plenty to work with. Using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt;, I could then combine the images into a 30 second video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg 
	-f image2 
	-pattern_type glob
	-export_path_metadata 1
	-i '*'
	-vf &quot;drawtext=text='%{metadata\:lavf.image2dec.source_basename\:NA}'&quot;
	-r 30 -c:v libx264 -b:v 1M -vf scale=640:-1
	../output.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twitter is very particular about what video format it accepts, you may need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/59056863/i-cant-upload-this-video-file-mp4-to-twitter&quot;&gt;fight with the conversion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is that video! This runs from 7 PM to 7 AM in the San Francisco Bay Area as well as the Central Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-media-max-width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Good morning Bay Area, you&amp;#39;re dealing with elevated AQI at a wildfire equivolent because of fireworks. Here&amp;#39;s the timelapse from 7 PM to 7 AM via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ThePurpleAir?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ThePurpleAir&lt;/a&gt; map &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/simonw?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@simonw&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s shot-scraper library.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Modesto went even higher, but the Bay traps the bad air until the morning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/hxRm1CpztP&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/hxRm1CpztP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Danny Page 🧮 (@DannyPage) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/1809233993432215596?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;July 5, 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can instantly see the impact of the fireworks. 200+ plus is dangerous for &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; if exposed to it for sustained amount of time. 100+ can hit sensitive groups hard. And given the nature of the Bay Area and the Oakland/Fremont hills, the toxic air can hang around. It’s dreadful during wildfire season and makes it all the more questionable that we would do this to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m increasingly of the opinion that fireworks should not be used at all, or at best sparingly in the best conditions for safe dispersal of the pollutants. There are fire risks, limb risks, and breathing risks that come with exploding toxic chemicals in the air. However, America disagrees with me, especially at 8:45 PM local time on July 4th each year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How and Why to Watch the T20 Cricket World Cup in the USA (2024)</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/how-to-watch-usa-cricket-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How and Why to Watch the T20 Cricket World Cup in the USA (2024)" /><published>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/how-to-watch-usa-cricket-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/how-to-watch-usa-cricket-2024">&lt;p&gt;USA Cricket is on it’s way to the Super 8. Not the motel, but instead the next round of the Men’s T20 Cricket World Cup. They finished second in their group with wins over Canada and Pakistan, a close loss to India, and a washout game against Ireland. This granted them 5 points and a berth into the next round. They’ll go on to face South Africa, West Indies (Known as the Windies), and England. Two wins in this round-robin group would likely be enough to see them through to the semi-finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;definitions&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you’ve never seen a game of cricket before, where do you even start to understand this cousin of baseball? Here are a few terms to start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Runs&lt;/em&gt;: Like in baseball, the goal of the game is to score the most runs possible. In baseball, you have to round all 4 bases to score a run. In cricket, you merely have to run 20 meters to the other side of the &lt;em&gt;Pitch&lt;/em&gt; to score a run. If you hit the ball out of the field, it’s 4 runs if it bounced on the way out, 6 runs if it clears the boundary before landing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wicket&lt;/em&gt;: This when is when the batter is out. In baseball, a batter would get to go again after getting out. In cricket, once you get out, you are done for the match. You get 10 wickets before your team is done playing offense. You can get out if the ball is caught before bouncing, the ball hits the stumps (also called a wicket) on delivery, or hits the stump before you reach the other side of the pitch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overs&lt;/em&gt;: This divides up the innings. The bowling team delivers (pitches) 6 balls per Over. There are 20 Overs per side in T20 cricket (hence the name). ODI - One Day International - has 50 Overs per side. Once you’ve exhausted all the overs, your team is done batting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Innings&lt;/em&gt;: Each team gets 1 of these in T20 cricket. (Why is it plural then? Who can say.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to bring it all together, &lt;strong&gt;when your team bats first, you want them to score as many runs as possible in 20 Overs before you have 10 Wickets.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your team is batting second, your team is &lt;strong&gt;chasing the target&lt;/strong&gt; set by the first team. Once you achieve the target, have lost 10 wickets, or used 20 overs, the match is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scorelines&quot;&gt;Scorelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down a few scorelines to understand why there are fractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/views/assets/img/canada-vs-usa.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Canada Vs USA - T20 World Cup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada batted first. They scored 194 runs, with 5 of their batters going out in 20 overs. USA batted second, and needed to hit a target of 195. They successfully did so by scoring 197 runs in 17.4 Overs. (17 full overs, and 4 of the 6 balls delivered in the 18th over). They only had 3 batters go out. (197/3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bit of parlance that I believe is left over from Test Cricket, this is denoted with “winning by 7 wickets” - but more importantly is “winning by 14 balls”. Given the 120 balls available to score the points, it lets us know how many resources they had left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/views/assets/img/pakistan-vs-usa.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pakistan Vs USA - T20 World Cup&quot; /&gt;
In one of the most tense matches for this newer cricket fans, USA had to chase again. Pakistan had 7 batters go out as they scored 159 runs. USA needed to score 160 runs to win. However, they only tied at 159 runs. Even though they only had 3 batters to go out, that’s not used as a tie breaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teams went to a Super Over, which is a single over for both teams. USA batted first and scored 18 runs with 1 out (18/1), setting a target of 19 for Pakistan. If they scored 18, it would be a second Super Over. However, Pakistan only scored 13, and the USA won their second match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/views/assets/img/india-vs-usa.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;India vs USA - T20 World Cup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave this to the reader! Can you answer the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who batted first and who batted second?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many runs did each team score?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many overs did each team play?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there was supposed to be a match against Ireland, but it got rained out. Rain Outs give a point (wins 2 points) and the USA scored 5 points in the group, enough to get second and advance to the next round. This result also guarantees the US a spot in the 2026 T20 World Cup!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr&lt;/strong&gt;: hit dingers, don’t get out, and win international acclaim. (And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/news/asian-america/saurabh-netravalkar-leads-team-usa-t20-world-cup-oracle-career-rcna157248&quot;&gt;more PTO from Oracle)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-resources&quot;&gt;More Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.espncricinfo.com/&quot;&gt;ESPN CricInfo&lt;/a&gt; - The best cricket scoreboard with lots of live commentary and stats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NZGLHdcw2RM&quot;&gt;Netflix “Explained” on Cricket&lt;/a&gt; - A great short video that explains the overall history of Cricket and some of the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.willow.tv/&quot;&gt;Willow TV&lt;/a&gt; - $10 a month to stream cricket. You can watch the whole World Cup here, and next month is Major League Cricket, the US’s domestic T20 Cricket league.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">USA Cricket is on it’s way to the Super 8. Not the motel, but instead the next round of the Men’s T20 Cricket World Cup. They finished second in their group with wins over Canada and Pakistan, a close loss to India, and a washout game against Ireland. This granted them 5 points and a berth into the next round. They’ll go on to face South Africa, West Indies (Known as the Windies), and England. Two wins in this round-robin group would likely be enough to see them through to the semi-finals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pushing your Custom Jekyll build to GH-Pages</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/jekyll-push-to-gh-pages-branch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pushing your Custom Jekyll build to GH-Pages" /><published>2020-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/jekyll-push-to-gh-pages-branch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/jekyll-push-to-gh-pages-branch">&lt;p&gt;I spent an hour or two trying to find a good script on how to push custom Jekyll builds to Github Pages. Surprisingly, they don’t allow you to target a specific folder for the build and keep just one branch. (Outside of /docs, but I couldn’t find a way to build Jekyll in /docs) - There was some complicated ways to setup Github Actions or other one-off solutions to build to a new branch. However, I finally found a solution that works for me, and I’ve compiled it here for my own reference and maybe it’ll help you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site&lt;/code&gt; is your build folder.
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; can be any other branch if you have a different name or need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-rf&lt;/span&gt; _site
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;_site/&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; .gitignore
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git worktree add dist gh-pages
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;script&quot;&gt;Script&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a new file called  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;push-to-gh-pages.sh&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;jekyll build  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This can be whatever your build command is&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;_site
git add &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--all&lt;/span&gt;
git commit &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Build at &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt; +&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'%Y-%m-%d %H:%M:%S'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
git push origin gh-pages &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--force&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ..
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it Execute permission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ chmod +x push-to-gh-pages.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have all that set up, you can make any changes you need in your repo, then after completing your work, you can make &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./push-to-gh-pages.sh&lt;/code&gt; part of your deploy process and see changes on your *.github.io site!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;citations&quot;&gt;Citations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/cobyism/4730490#gistcomment-2375522&quot;&gt;Gist with a ton of info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/33172857/how-do-i-force-a-subtree-push-to-overwrite-remote-changes&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow with my specific need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://musteresel.github.io/posts/2018/01/git-worktree-for-deploying.html&quot;&gt;More on Git Worktree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I spent an hour or two trying to find a good script on how to push custom Jekyll builds to Github Pages. Surprisingly, they don’t allow you to target a specific folder for the build and keep just one branch. (Outside of /docs, but I couldn’t find a way to build Jekyll in /docs) - There was some complicated ways to setup Github Actions or other one-off solutions to build to a new branch. However, I finally found a solution that works for me, and I’ve compiled it here for my own reference and maybe it’ll help you!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Political Football</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/political-football" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Football" /><published>2017-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/political-football</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/political-football">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*lLjVZPeOpc2l08OVZlc2DA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;“John Mara’s anxiety soon seemed unwarranted. Only a small portion of 1,500 active NFL players kneeled or sat during the anthem, and after the NFL season ended, the issue died down. According to Google Trends, interest in the anthem protest had all but flatlined. When the NFL resumed in August 2017, only a few players — Marshawn Lynch, Michael Bennett, and Cliff Avril, to name a few — protested during the anthem. That is, until President Donald Trump weighed in…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more of my article about the NFL protests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoutline.com/post/2412/political-football&quot;&gt;The Outline.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“John Mara’s anxiety soon seemed unwarranted. Only a small portion of 1,500 active NFL players kneeled or sat during the anthem, and after the NFL season ended, the issue died down. According to Google Trends, interest in the anthem protest had all but flatlined. When the NFL resumed in August 2017, only a few players — Marshawn Lynch, Michael Bennett, and Cliff Avril, to name a few — protested during the anthem. That is, until President Donald Trump weighed in…”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being Antifragile with Sports Contracts</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/being-antifragile-with-sports-contracts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being Antifragile with Sports Contracts" /><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/being-antifragile-with-sports-contracts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/being-antifragile-with-sports-contracts">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*kKTr1RqfqwKQnf_A6i9cAg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;$25,000 contract! And look at that bonus for performing against the Canadiens.A few tweets popped into my timeline about how analytical types gauge contracts in hockey. I won’t go into specific player examples, but did want to make a few points about how teams can benefit from having small gambles with upside, rather than signing players with contracts that later become millstones if they don’t work out as expected for the team. Here are the tweets for context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AdamZHerman/status/768810984521728000&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AdamZHerman/status/768810984521728000&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/AdamZHerman/status/768810984521728000&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hockeyanalysis/status/768812872440901632&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hockeyanalysis/status/768812872440901632&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/hockeyanalysis/status/768812872440901632&lt;/a&gt;“THAT’S A BAD DEAL” will generally refer to contracts that have one or more of the following problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Older player that is/will decline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contract that costs too much for the player’s ability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contract term has too many years.
Way too many times a team will give out these bad contracts and fail to realize how very hard they are to get out from under. These contracts are &lt;strong&gt;fragile&lt;/strong&gt;, as defined by Nassim Nicholas Taleb:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fragility implies more to lose than to gain, equals more downside than upside, equals (unfavorable) asymmetry — Antifragile, Chapter 10In the NHL, contracts are guaranteed and thus your team is on the hook for the full duration and cap value. If it’s a long/expensive contract, you really need the player to live up that value. This means you’re starting behind before you get your first game out of the player! This also reduces your flexibility on the cap ledger and in the trade market. Other teams may not have the cap space to take on your player, or will give you worse players/draft picks in return. At the very best, he’ll slightly overperform: A $6 Million player who plays like a $8 Million player is nice, but it could be disastrous. (This is extremely true for goalies on long/costly contracts, signed after one good year)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, David Johnson notes that a lot of times analysts expect a player to play above his contract and it doesn’t work out. This is a good thing! Sometimes you’re wrong, but if the contract is structured as follows, only upside can come from it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Young player with many elite years left.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contract has a low cap hit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Has only a few years on the contract.
If you’re going to be wrong, it’s better to be wrong on a more flexible contract. Again to call upon Taleb, he would call these contracts &lt;strong&gt;antifragile&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Antifragility implies more to gain than to lose, equals more upside than downside, equals (favorable) asymmetry — Antifragile, Chapter 10You don’t give up a lot of cap space and the contract can be moved more easily. If you are correct, the upside is massive. The player could turn out to be a star and thus flipped to team for draft picks or you have a player playing at an $8 Million value for only $2 Million a year. At worst, you lose a few million. (And even then, there’s always space for 4th line guys on other teams, or they can contribute to the AHL team, so it’s never a huge loss)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sports has a lot of volatility and a smart team can take advantage of that. Teams, especially those with limited budgets, must look to reduce their downside and increase their upside when it comes to contracts. A similar lesson is for teams to collect draft picks for cheap and young players. All else being equal, a few small failed contracts will certainly be worth the massive gain of a breakout player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let me know if you have any questions, please share, and lastly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/dannypage&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">$25,000 contract! And look at that bonus for performing against the Canadiens.A few tweets popped into my timeline about how analytical types gauge contracts in hockey. I won’t go into specific player examples, but did want to make a few points about how teams can benefit from having small gambles with upside, rather than signing players with contracts that later become millstones if they don’t work out as expected for the team. Here are the tweets for context:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Has Social Media Spoiled The Olympics?</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/has-social-media-spoiled-the-olympics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Has Social Media Spoiled The Olympics?" /><published>2016-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/has-social-media-spoiled-the-olympics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/has-social-media-spoiled-the-olympics">&lt;p&gt;This morning, I saw &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-08-19/nbc-s-12-billion-olympics-bet-stumbles-thanks-to-millennials&quot;&gt;an article from Bloomberg&lt;/a&gt; that placed blame on Millennials for not watching the Olympics. It was almost too early in the morning to deal with something that (yet again 🙄) is blaming some larger problem on a large &amp;amp; diverse group of young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766635147806449665&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It should have been “&lt;a href=&quot;http://giphy.com/gifs/jennifer-lawrence-thumbs-up-ok-Fml0fgAxVx1eM&quot;&gt;Jennifer Lawrence Okay Gif&lt;/a&gt;”. Told you it was early in the morning.But I started to consider the words here from Steve Burke, NBCUniversal’s CEO:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We wake up someday and the ratings are down 20 percent,” the chief executive officer of NBCUniversal said at a conference. “If that happens, my prediction would be that millennials had been in a Facebook bubble or a Snapchat bubble and the Olympics have come, and they didn’t know it.”First off, companies can buy advertising on those platforms to reach those audiences and put streams on Facebook and Twitter if you’re worried about people not being aware of your large event. (Well, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vocativ.com/348357/the-olympics-bans-gifs/&quot;&gt;maybe not Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in a way, he’s right for the wrong reasons. Lots of people spend a lot of time in the social media bubble. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/06/business/facebook-bends-the-rules-of-audience-engagement-to-its-advantage.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;According to the NY Times&lt;/a&gt;, 50 minutes a day is spent on Facebook by the average user in one such example. Surely a lot of time is also spent on Twitter, Snapchat, and many other platforms. Most of these people aren’t ignorant of the Olympics. I’d say these platforms encourage knowing more about the Olympics through gifs, videos, and celebratory posts about various teams and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem: Between the hot takes, the rush to be first with that ‘original’ joke about how #LochteGate should have been called #LochMess, or trying to find the right gif to show &lt;a href=&quot;http://replygif.net/i/269.gif&quot;&gt;sadness&lt;/a&gt; at the US Women losing to Sweden… Social Media is the “Right Now”. Meanwhile, NBC’s strategy has been “Please wait until Primetime. Please!” It’s not working anymore. It may have been slightly a problem in 2012 when they would show replays of Swimming, and I was at the only person at the nightly Olympic watch party that knew the result. Now it’s a huge problem because everyone knows!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I (unscientifically) polled my followers on Twitter a few questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*BPeLu0W-JWiL6jEhsV0ehg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766646933679202305&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766646933679202305&lt;/a&gt;I wanted to gauge how many people are finding out the results before they were shown at night. Olympic Gymnastics were a huge draw for American viewers, given the dominant team. Over half of people who participated in the poll knew the result before they were watching, while a mere **7% **of the poll were able to watch spoiler-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766647595531919360&quot;&gt;Some may have watched live, some saw gifs and videos online, and other people got push notifications on their phone when the event was over.&lt;/a&gt; Even the NBC Sports app will spoil the event for you if you would like! And that can be an okay thing, as they want you to be aware of the Olympics. But… It doesn’t turn into Primetime viewing and then advertisers get less bang for their buck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*yhAshAinuWQQ2j5mIrT2ZQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766666734883438592&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/766666734883438592&lt;/a&gt;The reason “Live Sports” as a category of TV has continued to do well is because there is always drama. Even in 1 PM football games with two weak teams, some people may watch out of team loyalty or for fantasy football. But ultimately, people watch sports because they don’t know the outcome ahead of time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not emphasizing live viewing of their sports on all their platforms, NBC has risked that people will drop their interest from 8PM — 12AM EDT. Some still may watch, but the excitement has to do with the mechanics of the event, rather than the result. Some may watch the gymnastics portion for the amazement, but you might not sit through the entire volleyball match. In fact, very few sports matches will ever be replayed. There’s no long-tail for sports. Very few DVD sets, except for the free ones that come with a new Sports Illustrated subscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not a problem in the past. The ‘Miracle On Ice’ game was on tape delay, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miracle_on_Ice#Game_summary&quot;&gt;many thought it was broadcast live.&lt;/a&gt; But that could not happen today. You wouldn’t hold a large event and hope people still tune in for the drama of the unknown result 3 hours later. Perhaps that’s why NBC has leaned even more on the biographies and life stories; because otherwise, the result is just a Google search away and the perfect moment from that event is being retweeted 10,000 times in the form of a six-second Vine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBC has it bad now, but they are going to have an even worse time in 2018 (Pyeongchang, South Korea), 2020 (Tokyo, Japan) and 2022 (Beijing, China). They are respectively ahead by 13, 13, and 12 hours. That means most of the important results will happen overnight for American viewers. Viewers in NYC may have to wake up at 5 in the morning to catch the 100 meter sprint finals! If they embrace internet streaming in a larger way, they may do okay. But as information becomes more widely available and at the forefront of our digital lives, TV networks will have to realize that they need to let go of their idea of Primetime being the golden hours in television. They must create better streaming solutions that are user friendly. Or at the very least, a playlist of events I can watch on my phone when I wake up before reading someone blaming Millennials. Again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. I didn’t mention NBC’s poor production values. Commentators in Gymnastics not meeting the bare minimum of explaining to the audience why deductions were being taken. There was no rhyme or reason given to the audience to guide them to further understanding. Another issue was way too many commercials. Heck, I think Ashton Eaton starred in more commercials than his time being shown in the primetime coverage. Turns out he won back to back Gold in the Men’s Decathlon. But Ryan Lochte gets more coverage in providing his own spin. 🤔&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently BBC had really good coverage: I’ll be curious to see their viewing numbers. It could be down because of timezone concerns, but by all accounts it was good viewing. Meanwhile, NBC definitely dropped the ball despite their timezone advantage, one that will really trouble them in the next 6 years. **Update: **The Canadian Broadcast Corporation released their numbers, and they had &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/mediacentre/rio-2016-on-cbcradio-canada-becomes-most-watched-summer-olympic-games-in-canadian-history.html&quot;&gt;their best watched Summer Olympics&lt;/a&gt;. Same timezone as NBC, so they must be doing something correctly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Sammich_BLT/&quot;&gt;Thanks, Brad!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please recommend and share if you liked this article, and let me know if I missed anything in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This morning, I saw an article from Bloomberg that placed blame on Millennials for not watching the Olympics. It was almost too early in the morning to deal with something that (yet again 🙄) is blaming some larger problem on a large &amp;amp; diverse group of young adults.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">South Carolinians are frantically Googling their own College, hours after they won the College…</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/south-carolinians-are-frantically-googling-their-own-college-hours-after-they-won-the-college" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Carolinians are frantically Googling their own College, hours after they won the College…" /><published>2016-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/south-carolinians-are-frantically-googling-their-own-college--hours-after-they-won-the-college</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/south-carolinians-are-frantically-googling-their-own-college-hours-after-they-won-the-college">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*TsW8_VWGX_dIBTG7X3WzSg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;The whole country is reeling after a milestone comeback win in Omaha to take the College World Series. And although leaders of the Chanticleers crowing over their victory, it seems many South Carolinians may not even know what they had actually cheered for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That confusion over what the win might mean for the Big South appears to have been reflected across the state on Thursday. Google reported sharp upticks in searches not only related to the competition but also about basic questions concerning the teams involved. At about 5 p.m. Eastern time, about one hour after the game ended, Google reported that searches for “what is coastal carolina” had more than tripled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the all-out attempts by either side to court baseball fans, Cleers were not only mystified by what would happen if they won the C.W.S — many seemed not to even know what Coastal Carolina is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Coastal Carolina? To be fair, that question will now take on a much deeper significance than perhaps Google’s users realized when they typed that into their browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;😘 Love ya, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-switch/wp/2016/06/24/the-british-are-frantically-googling-what-the-eu-is-hours-after-voting-to-leave-it/&quot;&gt;WaPo.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The whole country is reeling after a milestone comeback win in Omaha to take the College World Series. And although leaders of the Chanticleers crowing over their victory, it seems many South Carolinians may not even know what they had actually cheered for.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Sports Journalism Will Not Be Automated</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/the-future-of-sports-journalism-will-not-be-automated" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Sports Journalism Will Not Be Automated" /><published>2016-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/the-future-of-sports-journalism-will-not-be-automated</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/the-future-of-sports-journalism-will-not-be-automated">&lt;p&gt;#### At Least Until Everything Else Is 🤖&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*YDTILWQ1ZziRjwf3AxGYjQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Campus Party Europe - &lt;a href=&quot;https://flic.kr/p/cYpVLG&quot;&gt;https://flic.kr/p/cYpVLG&lt;/a&gt; — CC AttributeIt was announced today that the Associated Press &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ap.org/Content/Press-Release/2016/AP-expands-Minor-League-Baseball-coverage&quot;&gt;will cover all 142 MLB-affiliated minor league baseball teams.&lt;/a&gt; They have not hired a single journalist to do so. This is being done with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;https://automatedinsights.com&quot;&gt;Automated Insights&lt;/a&gt;, a startup based in Durham, NC that “analyzes patterns in big data and turns them into readable narratives.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automated_Insights&quot;&gt;(Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt; This certainly fits the needs of the AP, who would like to cover all news at scale. They’ve been doing this with NCAA Baseball and with quarterly earnings reports as well. But is this a positive for journalism? Does this help the readers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potentially, this frees up the person writing up game reports to investigate better stories. These stories already exist for each MiLB team (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20160627&amp;amp;content_id=186608306&amp;amp;fext=.jsp&amp;amp;vkey=recap&amp;amp;sid=t436&quot;&gt;Potomac Nationals&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20160628&amp;amp;content_id=186822626&amp;amp;fext=.jsp&amp;amp;vkey=recap&amp;amp;sid=t234&quot;&gt;Durham Bulls&lt;/a&gt;), and so you’d hope that the person in charge of these stories gets to write more interesting narratives. These recaps provide little more than the boxscore, perhaps there’s something else they could cover?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully so. In these times where journalists and &lt;a href=&quot;http://espn.go.com/mlb/story/_/id/13934900/federal-judge-grants-minor-league-baseball-players-conditional-class-status-wage-lawsuit-major-league-baseball&quot;&gt;minor league players are having trouble getting paid&lt;/a&gt;, both could benefit from more coverage. There’s plenty of great stories waiting to be told with teams that aren’t covered very closely. The Sonoma Stompers &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.excellesports.com/news/female-baseball-players-minor-league/&quot;&gt;will be starting two women on Friday&lt;/a&gt;, but the automated game recap might only remark on how “Kelsie Whitmore hit for a double in the bottom of the second” and completely miss the history of the moment. Or perhaps the automated story about the Washington Spirit vs Orlando Pride game would note that there was a prolonged minute of continued Orlando possession at 48:30, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.excellesports.com/news/pride-spirit-fans-players-stand-together-orlando-washington/&quot;&gt;miss the importance of what happened&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ahead of the game, fans were instructed to stand and clap for the entirety of the 49th minute. Play would continue as fans paid their respects, just as life trudges on in the wake of horrific violence. When the game clock read 48:00, no directive was issued, but slowly, all across the stadium, fans came to their feet. For that minute, the hate and bigotry that fueled the killing of 49 innocent people could be drowned out by the sound of nearly six thousand people applauding in support of love and acceptance. The players didn’t need to stop, but they did stop. The referee didn’t blow his whistle; the ball didn’t go out of bounds. &lt;strong&gt;Instead, twenty-two players from various nations, backgrounds, and lifestyles responded to the aching tug of human compassion, pausing to honor the lives of 49 people with stories so similar yet different to their own.&lt;/strong&gt;Fast forward to 3:53 to see the pause in action — NWSL Youtube&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.excellesports.com/news/author/caitlin-buckley/&quot;&gt;Caitlin Buckley&lt;/a&gt; nailed something that would be missed by an automated box recap: the emotion and the bigger importance of the game. I believe that proponents of automated reporting have missed the importance of distilling the human side of the game, rather than the numbers. In 2015, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poynter.org/2015/resistance-is-futile-ap-to-use-computers-to-cover-baseball-games/344335/&quot;&gt;Ed Sherman for Poytner opined&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A computer can’t write like Grantland Rice and deliver an epic lede that begins “Outlined against a blue-gray, the Four Horseman rode again.” Then again, nobody has written like that in more than 80 years.I don’t believe that to be true. Many journalists, including the website named after him (RIP Grantland) to outlets like Excelle Sports, are proving that wrong. They are telling the stories that aren’t being covered by the AP or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DannyPage/status/736604043653578752&quot;&gt;the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;. There are stories to be told, and even if they don’t have the flourish of Rice’s prose, it would be a shame if they weren’t told at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Another worry of mine that didn’t fit the greater story: Technology like this is great for distilling numbers and making them readable for humans to interpret. But we should always question the biases are going into that algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Pinboard/status/744595961217835008&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;🎉 Thanks for reading, please share, and you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/dannypage&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">#### At Least Until Everything Else Is 🤖</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop Using Google Trends</title><link href="https://danny.page/views/stop-using-google-trends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop Using Google Trends" /><published>2016-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://danny.page/views/stop-using-google-trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://danny.page/views/stop-using-google-trends">&lt;p&gt;#### Alternatively titled ‘Be aware of context, and maybe start using Google AdWords’ Instead&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Trends is a very interesting product, as it gives us real-time data on how people are using Google. Google is the Address Bar of the Internet, so if you need information on a topic, just type in “Euros” and you’ll have the scores and times of every game of the UEFA Euros Championship. Google can then track that interest in a topic and we can see it. But what shouldn’t you use Google Trends for? Well, until people start using it appropriately, everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, a lot people learned how to search on the internet from Ask Jeeves. Just last week we saw a story about a woman who always searched politely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/06/16/482343107/a-bit-of-afternoon-cheer-google-charmed-by-grandmas-polite-searches&quot; title=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/06/16/482343107/a-bit-of-afternoon-cheer-google-charmed-by-grandmas-polite-searches&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Bit Of Afternoon Cheer: Google Charmed By Grandma’s Polite Searches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It’s been a rough week in the news. And it’s been a rough week in comment sections … and Facebook posts … and…&lt;/em&gt;www.npr.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/06/16/482343107/a-bit-of-afternoon-cheer-google-charmed-by-grandmas-polite-searches&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It’s not a stretch to think that many people’s interaction with Google and other search providers are by asking a question, instead of putting in a topic. Here’s one such example that Ben Casselman brought up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bencasselman/status/746368872526266369&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ben’s example gives us insight in how people use Google. With this knowledge, you can either be an asshole and assume that many people didn’t know who Mitt Romney is after the election, or perhaps we can more likely conclude that it’s a function of people’s search habits of researching a relevant topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*mzTBrfr8WpzostJbMb4a0g.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;But journalists would never insult people who are googling current events!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/04/21/if-you-have-no-idea-who-harriet-tubman-is-youre-not-alone/&quot; title=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/04/21/if-you-have-no-idea-who-harriet-tubman-is-youre-not-alone/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have no idea who Harriet Tubman is, you’re not alone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Yesterday, the Treasury announced that it was putting Harriet Tubman on the front of the $20 bill and booting Andrew…&lt;/em&gt;www.washingtonpost.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/04/21/if-you-have-no-idea-who-harriet-tubman-is-youre-not-alone/&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But if all of yesterday’s frantic Googling is any indication, plenty of Americans don’t even know who she is.Oh. “Frantic”. “don’t know”. — Maybe the real issue is that it’s not “any indication”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why: Google Trends is that it reports search numbers relatively within the date-range and in context of other trends. Here again are those reported numbers, but with wider date ranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*Os-6lZ-JLP2-i_MmndyYXw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Note how the Washington Post also said: “Plenty of Americans” — What does ‘plenty’ mean here? Remember, Trends is relative. And we can see this with the most recent Google Trends Freaking Outrage (GTFO):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-switch/wp/2016/06/24/the-british-are-frantically-googling-what-the-eu-is-hours-after-voting-to-leave-it/&quot; title=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-switch/wp/2016/06/24/the-british-are-frantically-googling-what-the-eu-is-hours-after-voting-to-leave-it/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The British are frantically Googling what the EU is, hours after voting to leave it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The whole world is reeling after a milestone referendum in Britain to leave the European Union. And although leaders of…&lt;/em&gt;www.washingtonpost.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-switch/wp/2016/06/24/the-british-are-frantically-googling-what-the-eu-is-hours-after-voting-to-leave-it/&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;They note that searches about the EU tripled. But how many people is that? Are they voters? Are they eligible to vote? Were they Leave or Remain? Trends doesn’t tell us, all it does is give us a nice graph with a huge peak. More likely, it’s a very small number of people, based on this graph that puts it in context with other searches in the region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*mA4iVZVb41Mf0bif-EUCCA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Sammich_BLT/status/746365855441657856&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/Sammich_BLT/status/746365855441657856&lt;/a&gt;But it’s giving plenty of people cover to insult the entire country, when it’s likely just a few people searching for something in a way that they always search for something. It makes “The British are frantically Googling what the EU is, hours after voting to leave it&lt;strong&gt;” absurdly **disingenuous without better numbers. **Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/u/e7e4a5be3f63&quot;&gt;Remy Smith&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@remysmith/very-interesting-article-ill-admit-to-having-succumbed-to-that-against-which-you-re-railing-f82fb88d6a23#.4818x0scj&quot;&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt; this out: The peak was merely ~1000 people! It’s ludicrous that so few people get turned into a massive story, but it underscores the need for context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m disappointed that this is how data is being used, and really drives home the need for people to understand the data before they use it incorrectly. Google Trends is an interesting tool, but please do a bit more research before using it. Beware, you can look quite foolish by solely depending on it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mattenglish.kinja.com/fivethirtyeight-hilariously-thinks-sudbury-ontario-des-1631081577&quot; title=&quot;http://mattenglish.kinja.com/fivethirtyeight-hilariously-thinks-sudbury-ontario-des-1631081577&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nate Silver Hilariously Thinks Sudbury, Ontario Deserves an NHL Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Last week, the hockey world was set ablaze by a (since-denied) story that the league was quietly planning a four-team…&lt;/em&gt;mattenglish.kinja.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mattenglish.kinja.com/fivethirtyeight-hilariously-thinks-sudbury-ontario-des-1631081577&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Come on, I had to include this one.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*jOgoTfBaajm0UgA1ick1_g.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Please share, please Google “who is Danny Page” to make my day, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/dannypage&quot;&gt;follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: [Another fantastic example of the “what is &lt;topic&gt;” phenomenon.](https://medium.com/@dannypage/south-carolinians-are-frantically-googling-their-own-college-hours-after-they-won-the-college-f9ab5b68f5cf#.xhq5wag35)&lt;/topic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PPS: The googling worked! I had added that request on the 29th. The funny part was the people googling “Who is Danny Page” before then, also adding weight to my hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*HITIxZIjIHuQZeg6TMX1Vw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/views/assets/img/1*MWJ9X_a5T714j9D1au-8ww.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">#### Alternatively titled ‘Be aware of context, and maybe start using Google AdWords’ Instead</summary></entry></feed>